Register of the Krymskoe Kraevoe Pravitel'stvo records
Hoover Institution Archives
Krymskoe Kraevoe Pravitel'stvo records
1918-1920
XX320
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
The Krymskoe Kraevoe Pravitel'stvo records consist of administrative files of the Chairman of the Council of Ministers, Minister of Foreign Affairs, Minister of Justice, and Minister of Internal Affairs concerning the relations of the Crimean Regional Government and the Constitutional Democratic Party with the Russian Volunteer Army and with the Allies.
Krymskoe kraevoe pravitel'stvo (1918-1919)
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Krymskoe Kraevoe Pravitel'stvo (Crimean Regional Government) refers to two regimes in the Crimean Peninsula during the years 1918 and 1919. After the Russian October Revolution in 1917, an ethnic Tatar government proclaimed the Crimean People's Republic. The first Crimean Regional Government was established on 25 June 1918 under German protection with Lipka Tatar General Maciej (Suleyman) Sulkiewicz as prime minister and minister of interior and military affairs.
After the withdrawal of German troops from Crimea, Sulkiewicz was succeeded by Crimean Karaite politician and former Kadet member Solomon Krym. This liberal, anti-Bolshevik regime included fellow former Kadet member Maxim Vinaver as foreign minister and Vladimir D. Nabokov as minister of justice. The collapse of the World War I Central Powers and the withdrawal of the Allies had made Crimea fully dependent on Russia again. The Crimean Regional Government began to crumble in early 1919.
On 2 April 1919, the Soviet Red Army occupied Simferopol and the second Crimean Regional Government was dissolved. The Crimean Socialist Soviet Republic was then established only to be retaken by White forces in June 1919. The Whites, under Anton Denikin and later Petr Wrangel, held Crimea until November 1920.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Krymskoe Kraevoe Pravitel'stvo records consist of administrative files of the Chairman of the Council of Ministers, Minister of Foreign Affairs, Minister of Internal Affairs, and Minister of Justice Vladimir Dmitrievich Nabokov, the father of Russian-American writer Vladimir Nabokov. The records include government reports, manuals, and other publications; news dispatches; clippings; and correspondence relating to activities of the Crimean Regional Government, as well as decisions concerning relations of the Constitutional Democratic Party with the Russian Volunteer Army and with the Allies.
Arrangement Statement
All series, organizational hierarchies, and folders maintain their original order and title when possible. Handwritten notes by collector found in various folders also detail the scope of the material.
Konstitutsionno-demokraticheskaia partiia.; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920); Crimea (Ukraine)--History.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; Ukraine--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Ukraine.
- Documents of Maksim Vinaver, Minister of Foreign Affairs in the Crimean Regional Government, 1918-1919
  - Telegraphic messages exchanged between Ekaterinodar and the Crimean Government, 1918 October - 1919 April (Box-folder 1: 1-3)
  - Bulletin Published by the Foreign Office of Crimea for the Allied Navy Now in the Port of Sevastopol, Nos. 1-3, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Bulletin Publié par le Ministère des Affaires Étrangères de Crimée pour les Escadres et les Troupes Alliées, Nos. 1-16, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Dernières Nouvelles, Supplément au "Bulletin Publié par le Ministère des Affaires Étrangères de Crimée pour les Escadres et les Troupes Alliées," Nos. 1, 2, 4, 5, 7, 8, 16-18, 23-25, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Documents relating to the correspondence between the Crimean Government and the Allies (letters from Colonel Ruillet, Admiral Amet, etc.), 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1: 7-8)
  - Orders issued by the Commander in Chief of Troops in Sebastopol; by General Subbotin, the Chief Inspector Ribarsky; also a memorandum on the Crimean Government presented to the Allies, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Correspondence with Greek authorities, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Correspondence with Constantinople authorities, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Sundry documents relating to the correspondence with the Volunteer Army and the Allies, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1: 12-15)
  - Correspondence with the authorities in Odessa, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Correspondence with [Vasilii Maklakov (Maklakoff)], Russian Ambassador in Paris, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Minutes of the Meeting of the Crimean Cabinet of 16 April 1919 (in French) (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Documents relating to the history of Denikin's army and of the Cadet Party; the Congress of the Party [of Narodnaia Svoboda] in Ekaterinodar (abstract from M. Vinaver's report on foreign policy); peace terms proposed by President Wilson (a printed document being a supplement to the Journal of the Crimean Government); minutes of the Conference at Novo-Dmitrievskaia on the 17 of March, 1918; the Conference of the Cadet Party with the Central Committee on April 29-30, 1919; a draft of the Provisional Constitution of the provinces occupied by the Volunteer Army, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes clippings.
  - A complete set of voting papers [ballots] for the elections to the Crimean Diet, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - A letter from Omsk signed by M. Ustrugov (Ustrugoff) (member of the Kolchak Government) concerning the political situation in Siberia, dated March 21, 1919; also a "true copy" of General Denikin's letter of September 17, 1918, concerning Turkestan and sundry papers, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Balance sheets and receipts, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 5-6)
- Documents of Solomon Samuilovich Krym, Chairman of the Council of Ministers in the Crimean Regional Government, 1919-1920
  - Original decisions of the Council of Ministers, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Information about the last events on the front, 1919 April 7 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Telegram from General Denikin to the Crimean Government, 1919 March 16 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Declaration of the Crimean Government presented to Admiral Golthorpe at Sebastopol, 1918 December 7 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Note by Minister Steven, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Extracts from notes of the Crimean events, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Various letters and reports, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 2: 13)
- Documents of Vladimir Dmitrievich Nabokov, Minister of Justice in the Crimean Regional Government, 1918-1919
  - Collection of the laws and orders of the Crimean Government, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Telegram from General Denikin, 1918 November 21 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - The project of the engineers [Voinovskii-Kriger] and [S. N. Chaev] relative to the construction of the Crimean Railway, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Project of the statute of the elections in the Sein [to the Crimean Diet], 1919 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Project of a Commission for the transformation fot he Crimean tribunals, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Correspondence and reports, 1918-1919
    - Statute of the Ministry of Justice, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2: 19-20)
    - Order of the Government relative to the nomination of the senators, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 21)
    - Organization of the Senate at Novocherkassk, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Projects of laws and decisions of the Government and various other documents, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 23)
- "Krymskoe Kraevoe Pravitel'stvo (The Crimean Regional Government)," by Minister N. N. Bogdanov (Bogdanoff), circa 1919 (Box-folder 2: 24)